Hello, and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan, and today we're going
to be practicing equilibrium problems.
The big idea here is we're going to
be putting together all the different
concepts that really get covered in terms
of introductory chemistry when you're
learning the basics behind equilibrium.
So this is going to be mainly a
practice problem video, putting
together all those major concepts.
So that way you can learn how to
work through all the different
types of problems that you'll see.
So in putting all this together,
well, what does it all entail?
Well, the first thing was is when you
learned about equilibrium is that there's
this forward and reverse reaction.
And when the rates of the two
two sides of the reaction become
equal, equilibrium is achieved.
Now behind all that, what essentially
governed that entire process was the
whole idea that collisions had to be
made, and they had molecules had to be
oriented the right way, and there had to
be activation energy that was required
for these different reactions to happen.
So you kind of learn that, okay,
concentration, temperature, uh,
depending on how much energy there
is, the pressure, the volume,
all these conditions play a role.
which is where we were really seeing
that, okay, well, we can try to, we can
essentially poke this different, this
metaphorical equilibrium beast with
a stick and see like, all right, how
is it exactly going to react to that?
And then we also learned about all
the different acids and bases and
how this different strengths play a
big role behind all of that as well.
Now, when we learn about all that,
that all kind of gets put together
into this concept of the K expression,
which is an equilibrium expression.
Where if you have a balanced chemical
reaction, you can write it as a k
expression where you just put the
products over the reactants, and
it can be used to describe how the
system will behave at equilibrium.
Will the reaction favor, be it by
creating more products, or will
it favor creating more reactants?
And that's what we're going to be diving
into during this video by going through
all these different practice problems.
So let's dive into it, we're going
to go through some of the important
things to remember before we do.
And we're going to be going through
a range of different problems
from very easy to very hard.
So that way you can get a big idea.
And if you're looking for a specific
problem, feel free to use the little
chapter markers in the description
or below the video to be able to
help you navigate the entire process.
Okay, let's go take a look.
All right.
The first thing that we have to remember
before we start is this concept reactants.
So whenever we have the products over the
reactants, what that entails is that we
are writing essentially the concentration.
Of each of the products.
And we're going to be raising them
to their powers of their co, which
is their coefficients, right?
So if I have, let's say C for example,
and it has the coefficient as little
C, we'd raise it up as a power.
Same thing with the, and then with
the little d with the lowercase
d to help represent that as well.
We would do the same thing
for the reactants, right?
We would put them into square brackets,
which just as a reminder, represented.
concentration in the form of molarity.
And then we would also apply their
coefficients to tell us what power
raise it to because concentration
plays a big role in how all
this, how all this gets changed.
Now, depending on what the K value
is, this is something that can
either be calculated if you know
all the concentrations, or it is
something that is given to you.
Now, depending on what the
size is, it tells a story.
If k is greater than 1, then that means
it's going to be favoring the products.
If k is less than 1, it
favors the reactants.
So when we refer to products,
this is usually saying, hey, this
is going to shift towards the
right hand side of the reaction.
And if we refer to it as reactants,
that's going to favor the left.
Now from there, you can also have k is
in the middle where it's equal to 1.
This is when the concentrations
are equal to each other.
This is a very, very rare situation, but
it is possible for this to happen too.
Now, the other thing to keep in mind
is when it comes to K, you're going
to see all these little subscripts
describing what type of K you have.
We essentially treat them all
relatively the same, but it can give
you a little bit of a snapshot of
what the problem is referring to.
Um, especially if you're thinking
about acids and bases or maybe
with water, it gives you an idea of
really what kind of problem you have.
So it is helpful to kind of
remember at least the ones
that pertain to your course.
So for people who are watching
this for introductory chemistry,
I'll mark them for my course.
But if you're looking for other ones for
your class, if you're another student.
Then you have to try to make sure
you verify that with your teacher.
So for here, we, there's
a big list of them, right?
So the first thing that we generally
start with is keq, which is
referring to EQ is equilibrium.
This is usually the
most generic form of it.
So for my course, this is usually one of
the most standard ways that we show this.
So with this one, we'll put a
little star next to it to tell
us, Hey, this is pretty normal.
The next one is KC, which is
referring to concentration.
This is also a pretty normal one because
we're always dealing with molarity.
Kw is with water dissociation.
When it comes to acids and bases,
this one is very, very normal as well.
There's Ka and Kb, which
are acids and bases.
Both of these are typically used
when we're referring to that as well.
Now with solubility product, this one is
hit or miss for introductory chemistry.
It depends on your teacher.
So for this one, if you're talking about
net ionic equations and you have to
write it as an equilibrium constant, then
it is pretty normal to represent this.
We will go through a couple
of examples in this video too.
Now the last two are pressure
or equilibrium via pressure
and equilibrium of formation.
These two typically you only
see in general chemistry one
or general chemistry two.
which is when you go into like
really advanced equilibrium problems.
These will not be covered in this video.
So if you were coming here to look for
this, then, you know, keep on moving,
unfortunately, um, with that particular
part, let's look into some other things
that we need to remember as well.
The last thing is, was
Le Chatelier's principle.
So we'll also be predicting how can
these different reactions shift.
So if we increase the concentration
or the temperature, pressure,
volume, or even add an enzyme.
If I want to poke the reaction
with a stick, what exactly is
going to happen as a result?
So that's going to be
our last little thing.
So let's go look at our first
problems and go through all the
different practice and see exactly
how we will conquer these problems.
So for the first example, one of the most
common problems you will get is it says
consider the reaction and then it asks
you to write the equilibrium expression.
So we have disulf we have
disulfur hexafluoride is going
to be reacting to making sulfur
fluoride and then fluorine gas.
So when these are made, what we're
going to be doing is we will take our
products and put it over our reactants.
So being like SF6 on the right hand
side, notice how it has a power of two.
So for its coefficient, so we are going
to put that outside of the brackets.
And then we have fluorine
on the right hand side too.
That one does not have a coefficient,
so we do not need to write it.
And then we have our reactants as well.
So it's S2F6, and we will
put that inside of brackets.
And then this entire thing is going
to be equal to KEQ, which is what we
were trying to solve in the problem.
Now when you have this expression,
one of the most common types of things
that you will have to do is is use
it to try to define and, and to work
around how the formula exactly works.
So for this particular problem,
what we are going to be doing is
using the expression, calculate K eq
using the following concentrations.
Now, the thing about this is, one of the
things that's very frustrating about these
problems is it's very easy to accidentally
get the formula incorrect, so you want
to make sure you double check your work.
Remember, solids and liquids are
never included in that formula.
The other thing is you want to
make sure you have your powers
being used properly as well.
That's also a very common error
for many of these problems.
So what we're going to do is we're just
going to plug all these concentrations in.
So the first one is SF6, which
I actually miswrote, I should
have said SF2 by mistake.
So let's fix that in our problem.
So this is SF2.
So let's plug that formula in.
So that was 2 molar, and that
is going to be to a power of 2.
And then we have fluorine,
which is also 2 molar.
and that is to a power of one.
And then what we are going to do
is divide all of this by one molar.
And that is to a power of one as well.
Now, when we put all this
into our calculators, this is
going to be solving for K eq.
Now, so when we're doing these different
numbers, it's really easy for it to
kind of, it allows you to kind of
predict which way it's going to go.
And then you can also do Le Chat Lies too.
So with this answer, we get an
answer of eight for our problem.
So we're going to write that down.
So with this type of problem, what this
can essentially tell us to is we can kind
of determine a little bit more about this.
So one thing about it is like,
well, based on that KQ, are
there more reactants products or
an equal amount at equilibrium?
So this is where it's important
to remember your K trends.
This is a very common question
that's typically put on equilibrium
exams, especially on final exams that
may contain equilibrium problems.
So the one thing you got to
remember is, well, it's all about
K or which direction does it go?
Is it greater than or less than one?
In this case, we have a
K that is equal to eight.
So that's a lot greater than one.
So what that's going to tell us
is that this particular reaction
is going to be favoring products.
All right.
So it's going to be going towards
the right hand side of the reaction.
So you're going to have more products in
your, in your end reaction at equilibrium.
Now, the last thing that I
asked is, well, let's think
about Le Chatelier's principle.
If fluorine is removed, what would happen?
Well, so Le Chatelier's principle
is all about trying to think how
is the system going to react?
So if we remove Fluorine, the system
is going to freak out because all of
a sudden all the fluorine is missing.
So it's like, well, if you kind of all
of a sudden, I don't know, maybe this
might be a little too real, but you
look in your bank account and all the
money's gone, you're going to freak out.
Well, what are you going to do?
Well, you're going to try to earn more.
So how are you going to try to do that?
Right.
And try to earn more.
Well, the entire reaction is going to
tip in the direction towards fluorine,
meaning we're going to be favoring
that right hand of the reaction.
Even more heavily, because it's going
to want to generate more as a result.
One thing that if you can kind of
remember, if we take something away,
we're going to shift towards it, right?
So if you take, you shift towards.
So in this case, it's going to be
shifting to the right or in this case
towards the products help create.
More fluorine as a result and you can
kind of analyze that too regarding
the other species what would happen
So that's another common question is
well, what would happen to the sf2?
Concentration.
Well being that fluorine went down
as a result afterwards sf2 would go
up in terms of s2 f6 that one would
decrease because more reactants
are turning into products So it
depends on how the problem is worded.
You got to think, well, what
would happen after equilibrium
is reached after the problem?
Let's go take a look at another example.
So in our next example, we're going to
be practicing writing more equilibrium
expressions, but we're going to be
essentially reusing a lot of the rules
that was covered in my equilibrium video.
Which, one of the things is that we only
include gases and aqueous substances
when we're talking about equilibrium.
Solids and liquids generally are never
included in most equilibrium expressions,
um, being that essentially this is all
about how molecules are going to be moving
around and it's generally more free.
And we're generally also talking about
very, very small concentrations as well.
So we're, liquids are generally too
concentrated and then solids do not,
are a little bit more complicated to
actually explain that these principles.
So we're only ever referring
to aqueous and gases.
So the first thing is when we look
at this first problem, you want to
look at what all the phases are.
So we have SiH4 plus
2Cl2 plus SiCl4 plus 2H2.
And the thing is that you'll notice with
all of them is that all of them are gases.
So what we can do is we can write
this problem just like normal.
So on the right hand, so we
always do products first.
So we would write S I C L 4 as a product,
being that it doesn't have a coefficient
that would be to the power of one.
Then we have H 2 that
has a coefficient of two.
So what we would end up doing is making
sure that is to the power of two.
Then from there we put
everything with the reactants.
So we have SIH four to the power of
one, and then we would do CL two to the
power of two because it's coefficient is
a two in the front, not the subscript,
but the coefficient in this case.
So that is how we would write a
proper equilibrium expression.
Now, if we were to go to the
next one, which is PCL five,
turns into PCL three and CL two.
We want to check to make sure
everything's balanced, but the one
thing is that you might notice is that,
well, we have a liquid in the problem.
So what that means is we're not going
to end up including it in our KEQ.
So we'll still do products over reactants.
So we have CL2, and then we want
to put that all over the reactants,
which is going to be PCL5.
So that will be down in
the denominator, so PCL5.
And being that that does not
have a power, this would be the
correct equilibrium expression.
Now for the next one, we have FeO,
that's a solid, plus CO gas, and FeS.
So what we're going to be doing here
is once again checking all the phases.
So you see that we have a solid, and
then another solid, so we're not going
to include those, only the gases.
So when we write this, we
do products over reactants.
So we have CO2 to the
power one all over CO.
And you're going to see like,
Oh, these are pretty easy, right?
It's all about products or reactants.
Say that to yourself, products over
reactants, products over reactants.
That's something that's going to kind of
stay home for a lot of different points
in chemistry, especially if you have to
take gen chem one or gen chem two as a,
as either chemistry or biology major.
You're going to see that pop up in
different sections of the class.
All right.
Now the last one, what we have
is once again, we're looking
for all the different phases.
So one thing that we can see is
that, oh, we have a solid here, so
we're not going to include that.
So when we do products,
we have K and O three.
And one thing that we can kind of notice
is that it's has a two coefficient.
So we'll put a power two in front of it.
Then we do our reactants, so we have
PbNO3, and that's going to be 2, that's
a subscript of 2, outside of brackets.
And then we have our KCL, so
we'll put that in another color
just to help emphasize it.
And that's to a power of 2 because of
the coefficient on the left hand side.
Okay, so we want to make sure that
we kind of follow along with all
these, plugging them all in, remember
products over reactants, place your
powers, um, so it's just putting your
coefficients as powers, and this is
how we do these kinds of problems.
Let's go on to our next type of problem.
So one of the very common problems is
you doing Le Chatelier's principle.
And this is something that usually
you have to memorize the different
trends unless you're able to kind
of visualize how the reactions
shift forward and reverse.
If you're planning on being a chemist
or a biologist, I would recommend
remembering the trends because it
does help you be able to predict and
understand how chemical reactions occur.
But if you're just trying to get through
this course, then at least knowing them
until you get to the end of your exam.
Um, but a lot of them kind of
follow some common sense kind of
things about how reactions work.
Um, the more you kind of realize of how it
relates to your actual world around you.
So, one of the things is, well,
what direction would equilibrium
shift for the following changes
in this endothermic reaction?
Okay, so it's being told what
kind of reaction we have.
So being that it says that
it's endothermic, one thing
that you have to remember is,
well, where do you place heat?
Is heat being absorbed or is it released?
Endo is a positive value.
It's something that is
being, is being absorbed.
So, what you would do is, this is going
to be a reactant on the left hand side.
If it was XO, then it would be written
as a product on the right hand side.
This is, could affect how you
would list some of these different
values and how they would change.
So, the first one is, well, if carbon
monoxide is removed, what would occur?
So, if I remove CO, well, which
direction is the reaction going to shift?
Well, it's going to panic and realize
that, oh, all of this is missing.
So it's going to end up shifting towards
the right to create more CO as a result.
So with this one, we will shift
towards the products as a result.
If I go to the next one, which is
what if temperature is decreased, what
would exactly happen in that result?
Well temperature, the way that we treat
it, it's very similar to a concentration.
If the reaction's getting
really, really cold, it's gonna
be like, well, how do I what?
What do I do?
Well, if you get really cold in real
life, well, what's the first thing you do?
You add?
Either add more layers, turn
up the heat, you do something
to warm yourself up, right?
That common sense of what
do you do in everyday life.
So if that were to happen, we
would shift the reaction in
response to the reactant side.
So we will shift it the other way.
So reactants, and we would try to heat
ourselves up by making more reactants.
Now what if carbon was removed?
So carbon, if you can see right
here on the, on the left hand
side, notice how carbon is there.
So what if I remove it?
Do I follow the same trend I
did before, where if I take
something away, I shift towards it.
But notice one thing next to it, right?
It is a solid.
Ooh.
So what does that mean?
Well, if you remember, how would
you write the K expression?
Well, would you include a
solid in your final expression?
And the one thing you can
remember is you don't.
So would it have a change in this case?
No, there would be no effect.
So if you have a solid or a
liquid, it doesn't do anything.
So that's one thing to remember, right?
It's less work for us for later.
All right.
Now, what if pressure is increased?
When it comes to pressure, the
thing that we have to do is we got
to look at the number of moles.
Well, on the different
sides of the reaction.
So if we want to increase pressure,
what it's going to do, it's going to
shift away from more moles of gas.
So one thing that we see is if you
look on the right hand side, we have
three moles of gas that we have the
two moles of CO, one mole of CO2.
So there's three total.
On the left hand side, well,
there is zero moles of gas.
So which way could it
go to relieve pressure?
And that way, how do
you, where can you go?
Where, where's it less crowded on the
left hand side, on the right hand side?
And one thing that you'll notice
is that, well, if I end up shifting
this to the left, Then it's
going to be a lot less crowded.
So we're going to be shifting
it towards the reactants if
we increased the pressure.
All right.
Now that's how we look at
Le Chatelier's principle.
Let's go take a look at our next example.
Consider the following example.
So if I have two SO2 and it's reacting
with oxygen gas to make sulfur trioxide
and I have a K that's equal to 680.
Now from that, if at equilibrium
we have the concentration of SO2.
Which is point 300 molar
oxygen, which is 0.150 molar.
And I ask, what is the
concentration of SO three?
How would you do that?
Well, for this particular problem,
if you need to find a concentration
of an individual species.
You need to rearrange the problem.
You need to re, you need to create your
K expression and then rearrange it.
So the first thing is, if I want to set
up my expression, well, you know that
680 is equal to K and then it's gonna be
equal to the products over the reactants.
So we have SO three, which is what we
want, and all of that is gonna be over
SO two, which is to the second power.
And then also oxygen.
So now with that, what we're going to do
is we're going to rearrange the equation.
So that way we essentially
get everything by itself.
Um, we, you could kind of plug everything
into it right off the bat if you really
chose to, but it's usually whenever
you're doing this problem, it's sometimes
helpful to just kind of rearrange it
so you can kind of see how to use it.
So when you're rearranging this.
One thing that you would do is we'd
have 680 on the left hand side, and
then we would want to essentially
multiply both sides by the denominator.
So if I were to do that, where I
multiply the right hand side by the
denominator, so that way they'll
cancel, we'll multiply the 680 as
well, so that way it gets rearranged.
And as a result, you'll see that the
bottom cancels, and then what that's
all going to be equal to is SO3 squared.
So we almost have SO3 by itself, so what's
the last little thing that you have to do?
How do you remove a square?
Well, the opposite of a square
is a square root, right?
So what we're going to do is we will
square both, square root both sides.
And what you can see is this formula
that we kind of came with, came up
with on the right hand side is going
to be equal to SO3 as a concentration.
So now what we are going to do is we're
going to plug all of our numbers in.
So what we had, right, we had 680,
then our concentration of SO2.
was 0.
300, we'll square that, and
then times oxygen which was 0.
150 molar.
So when we plug all those values
in, what we are going to get as
a final answer is going to be 3.
0298 molar, and then we would round
that to 3 sig figs which would be 3.
03.
molar.
So that's how you would
solve for a concentration.
I'd recommend trying it on your own just
so you can try to rearrange it yourself.
It's all, you know, it takes
a little bit of algebra, but
sometimes you will have to do this.
This is a very common thing to have to
do when it comes to pH problems, because
you're usually solving for maybe the
hydronium or the hydrogen concentration.
Or the hydroxide concentration, which
you could then convert to pH or POH and
all those different species as well.
Let's take a look at our next example.
So for the next one, which is all about
solubility products, and I ask you write
the net ionic equation, then the KSP.
So if you have to define a
solubility product, it's all about
how does it dissolve in solution.
So the first thing is, well,
defining what is led to iodide.
So when you see the Roman numerals, the
first thing for you to get out of your
head is thinking that this is a subscript.
A lot of students that I see think
that that is a subscript, but that's
telling you what the variable charge is.
So being that is led next to an iodine,
we will swap drop, um, so that that
charge of two will get traded down.
And then that one, that one is going
to get traded down on the other side.
So what we will end up having is
lead I2 as our final structure.
And what we are going to be curious
about is, well, how is that going to
dissolve or if it can even dissolve?
One thing is that you'll
notice is that lead iodide is
actually very, very insoluble.
It's generally considered to be a
solid, but it can still, even though
something is labeled as insoluble, it
still can break down into its ions.
It just usually has a
very, very small K value.
So the way that we would represent the
dissociation equation is we would write
lead 2 and then we would reset the
ions So being that we have I2, we don't
just write I2 like this That's a no no.
The 2 would actually get brought in front
because it's like taking lead iodine and
then Smashing it into a million pieces.
So what exactly would
happen when you break it?
It's gonna go into all of its ions So
being that these are both in solution,
they are considered to be aqueous.
So what we would do is our
products over reactants.
So you will quickly see that the KSP is
only equal to the products because our
reactant is insoluble in this situation.
So we would write it just like this.
Now the thing is, how do you
interpret these different K values?
What they're telling you is
how soluble something is.
So the bigger the K
value, the more soluble.
So let's say if I had the KSP for a
bunch of different, different salts.
So I have lead sulfate, aluminum
phosphate, silver chloride, and
then I have their respective Ks.
So how do we choose?
Well, whichever one is the biggest
would be your most soluble.
So when you kind of look through
these, well, you see lead sulfate has
the biggest number out of all these.
So this would be your most soluble.
Whereas aluminum phosphate would
be your least soluble because
it's your tiniest number.
So this would be your answer
here, right, is this top choice.
Let's go on to our next example.
So for our last example, what we
are going to be doing is writing
the Ka for the following acid.
So, it's very common that you will
have to write Ka expressions or even
Kb expressions for general chemistry.
So one of the things that we
will do is when we are writing
these, we typically are writing
how they would react with water.
So if I have HIO3 and it's reacting
with water, well, the first thing
is, is you have to label the acid
and the base because that determines
how they are going to behave, right?
Acids donate protons.
So what's gonna happen is the H from the
I Otic acid is gonna donate to water.
So when we write that, we are
going to write our IO three minus
and then our H three oh plus
for our other expression, right?
Or sorry for our other product.
So now that we have that, what
we are gonna now do is write RKA,
which is products over reactants.
So being that the only thing here is that
that we don't include is water because
that is a liquid The rest of these would
all be considered aqueous Yet they're ions
and that they're soluble in a mixture.
So we would write our products all
over our reactants Okay, so we have
io3 minus HO3 plus All over H, I,
O, 3, that's our final piece, okay?
And that's how we'd write Ka and Kb.
Now the last thing is, sometimes
you have to interpret the
strength of an acid or base.
So depending on what the size of your
Ka value is, determines the strength.
Just like we did with Ksp.
The larger the number, the more ions
that are being generated in the solution.
The more ions, the stronger it is.
So the stronger the electrolyte, the
stronger the acid, the stronger the base.
And you can also do equilibrium
problems with these two where it comes
to Le Chatelier's principle, um, or
just determining how acids and bases
behave with figuring out pH or pOH.
All right, so this has been my summary of
all the major problems that you generally
will see in terms of equilibrium.
This is obviously not all of them.
But it's more practice to help you
master them and to go through them.
So thank you so much for listening.
If this helped you, please let me know.
Please reach out to me with any questions.
Feel free to either email me,
message me, or if you're just
watching the video on YouTube, you
can comment below with questions.
Um, but thank you so much for that.
And I really appreciate that.
Um, and if this is your first time
here, Please hit that like and
subscribe button, and if it did help
you, please watch my other videos.
They're all here to help
students just like you.
This has been Dr.
Dan here, and thank you so much
for listening and trying to learn
a little bit about chemistry.
I'll see you all later now.
Bye now.